Could you tell me what room
Colonel Roy Mustang is staying in?
ロイ·マスタング大佐の病室はどこかね
Let's see...
え～っと…
May I have your name, please?
お名前を伺ってもよろしいでしょうか
The name's Nox. Doctor in private practice.
ノックスってぇ町医者だ
He'll know right away.
取り次いでもらえば分かるよ
Hey, princess.
お嬢ちゃん
It's been a while.
お久しぶりです
Who might that be?
そちらの方は
I need him here for a reason.
ちょっと訳ありでな
まあいわゆる  奥の手ってやつさ
He's what I'd call my trump card.
So, is he down in the dumps?
どうだい
やっこさん落ち込んでるかい
The main method of cultivation in the Ishbal area is double-cropping,
イシュヴァール地方の作物の栽培は
二毛作が主であり…
はい　それ　間違い
Bzzzt, try again.
They raise the same crop semiannually.
二毛作でなく二期作ね
You expect to gain their trust like this?
んなことじゃ
信頼を得るなんて無理ですよ
I know!
分かっている
Moving on.
はいはい
So what crop do they raise with that method?
じゃあ　その二期作で何を作っていますか
Barley and cotton.
麦と綿花だ
Correct.
正解
So you DO know your stuff.
分かってるじゃないですか
なめるな
Don't underestimate me.
一応調べていたんだよ  以前からな
I've been doing some research for a while.
He's planning to solve the Ishbalan crisis before becoming the Führer President.
大総統になる前に
イシュヴァールの問題を解決するんですって
"Solving"?
解決って…
But first things first, "becoming the Führer President"?
いや　そもそも大総統になるって…
Is that you, Dr. Nox?
その声は　ノックス先生か
Yo.
Looks like... you're doing okay.
なんというか　元気そうだな
Yeah.
These guys won't leave me alone.
こいつらがうるさくてな　休ませてくれん
No breaks, no nothing.
いや　そうじゃなくて
Not exactly what I meant.
お前さん　目が…
Aren't your eyes...
Yeah.
Apparently, it's the punishment Truth gave to someone who dreamt of the future.
未来を夢見た者に
真理が与えた罰だそうだ
Are you okay?
大丈夫なのか
Not sure about that.
さあ　どうかな
Either way, I can't stop here.
だが　私は立ち止まるわけにはいかんのだ
Führer President...
大総統…いや　その前に
Well, to take care of Ishbal first.
イシュヴァールを
The Ishbal Annihilation...
イシュヴァール殲滅戦…
That was what started everything.
あれがすべての始まりだった
Yup. Both for you, and for me.
そうだな
あんたにとっても　オレにとっても
I'm going to set things right.
そのケジメをつける
Meaning?
ケジメ…
First, I'm going to open up the areas in Ishbal that are currently off-limits.
まず　イシュヴァール閉鎖地区を開放する
Then, I'm going to allow the Ishbalans living in each slums back to their Holy Land.
そして　各スラムにいるイシュヴァール人を
その聖地に帰す
There's much more to be done.
やることはまだまだある
We were able to overcome the crisis
thanks to Scar and the other people of Ishbal.
今回の事件　スカーや
イシュヴァールの人たちのお陰で
乗り切れたんです
We're in their debt, after all.
その恩返しをしなくちゃいけませんしね
Colonel, I brought the data you asked for.
大佐　頼まれていた資料
持ってきましたよ
It's not as if our sins will be forgiven,
but we want to start with what we can.
罪が消えるわけではないけれど
できることから始めたいんです
Christ, you lot...
ったく　どいつもこいつも…
Yo, it looks like they took the words out of our mouths, Dr. Marcoh.
マルコーさんよ
こっちから言う手間省けたようだぜ
マルコー
Marcoh?
Dr. Marcoh?!
ドクター·マルコーか
Colonel Mustang.
マスタング大佐
I've got a philosopher's stone right here.
ここに賢者の石があります
We should be able to get your vision back with this.
これで視力を取り戻せるのではないですか
You're right.
そうだな
I made this stone in the past by using the lives of Ishbalans.
この石はかつて私が
イシュヴァール人の命を使って
作ったものです
I have no right to say this, but if it's for the sake of reviving Ishbal, I'm sure they'll...
私が言うのはおこがましいとは思う
だが　彼らもイシュヴァール復興のためなら…
No, I cannot hear their voices.
いや　私は彼らの声を聞くことはできない
So this is a request from myself.
だからこれは　私個人の願いだ
I want to patch you up with this stone for the sake of Ishbal.
私はこの石であなたを治したい
イシュヴァールのために
They might get angry.
彼らは怒るかもしれないな
Fullmetal, too.
あと　鋼のも
だが　使わせてもらおう
But I'll gladly take your offer.
And with that, I'll give it my all.
そのうえで　私は全力を尽くす
But before that...
ただ　その前に…
...there's someone who needs the power of the stone more than I.
私より先にその石が必要な者がいる
私はその者の後だ
I can come after him.
Havoc General Store, happily serving for 80 years now!
はい
愛されて８０年　ハボック雑貨店
Oh, Breda. What's up?
ブレダ　どうした
What?! You want me to head down to Central NOW?!
何ぃ　今すぐセントラルに
What do you mean, "you'll find out when you get there"?
いや　「来れば分かる」って
お前な…
How are your wounds treating you, Scar?
傷の具合はどうだ　スカー
Why did you save me?
なぜ助けた
Initially to find out more about Eastern Alchemy,
もともと錬丹術を得るために
と思って助けたのだが
状況が変わった
but the situation has changed.
Mustang wants Miles for his new Ishbal policy.
マスタングのヤツが
イシュヴァール政策のために
マイルズをよこせと言いだしてな
で　貴様も連れていこうと思った
And so, I decided to take you along.
Not as "Scar," but as someone of the Ishbalan race.
もちろん　スカーとしてではなく
一イシュヴァール人としてだ
どうだ　イシュヴァラ教復興に尽力せんか
What do you say?
Won't you help us in reviving the Ishbalan religion?
We cannot let a religion and a culture so rich in history die out.
歴史ある宗教や文化を死なせてはならん
The death of a culture equates to the death of its people.
文化の死は民族の死だ
Save the people from death with your hands.
お前の手で民族を死から救え
The meaning of being kept alive...
生かされている意味…
So you want me to live for a bit longer to find what that is, huh, Brother?
もう少し生きて探せということか　兄者
Fine.
分かった　協力しよう
I'll help you out.
Take me wherever you please.
この体どこへなりと連れてゆくがいい
Okay, Miles. I'm leaving the rest to you.
よし　マイルズ　あとは任せた
Do things safely.
つつがなく執り行え
はっ
Roger.
That Mustang...
マスタングめ　スカーが生きていると知ったら
He'd probably be frightened to death
if he were to find out that Scar is alive.
さぞかし　肝を冷やすだろうよ
Scar.
スカー
What is your true name?
貴様　本当の名はなんという
I've died twice.
オレは二度死んだ
I don't exist in this world.
この世にはいない人間だ
Thus, I don't need a name.
名はなくていい  好きに呼べ
Call me whatever you please.
I see.
そうか
We'll meet again, Ishbalan.
また会おう　イシュヴァール人よ
You okay?
大丈夫か
I didn't imagine that my muscles would be this weak.
こんなに筋肉が衰えてるとは思わなかった
Want a ride on my back?
おぶってやろうか
Nah.
いや　いい　自分の足で歩く
I want to walk with my own two legs.
I'll take it slow, so you go on ahead.
僕はゆっくり帰るからさ
兄さんは先に帰っててよ
Nah. We left the house together.
いや　一緒に家を出たんだ
We have to go back together, too.
一緒に帰るさ
Well then, let's go.
じゃあ　一緒に帰ろっか
Yeah.
Brother, your leg...
兄さん　足…
Yeah... I haven't had maintenance on it in forever.
しばらく整備してねぇから
ちょっとな
Thanks.
ありがとう
For what?
何が
Nothing.
なんでもない
What the heck?
んだよ　変なヤツだな
Weirdo.
Oh yeah, I wonder if Lin and the others have arrived in Xing already.
そういえば　リンたち
もうシンに着いたかな
It's been two months since then, so I'm sure they have.
あれから２か月たつから
さすがにもう着いてるだろ
I hope May is okay...
メイ　大丈夫かな
Don't worry.
心配すんな　あいつに任しとけ
Just leave everything to him.
May...
メイ
Sir Al...
アル様
What's the matter?
どうしたの
Nothing.
いえ…
Hey you, the princess from the Chan clan.
チャン家の皇女
Lin Yao!
リン·ヤオ
Whoa, don't give me that scary look.
そんな怖い顔でにらむなって
You're such a klutz.
お前もバカだなぁ
よその国のゴタゴタにつきあって
In the end, you were unable to obtain a philosopher's stone because you were meddling in another country's affairs.
結局　賢者の石も手に入れられずか
The Yao clan will now be in control.
次の帝位はヤオ家のものだ
But don't fret.
でも　心配するな
Our clan will protect yours.
お前の家はヤオ家が
責任を持って守ってやる
I'm the man who even accepted the Homunculus Greed.
人造人間グリードですら
受け入れたこのオレだぞ
I'll accept the Chan clan along with all of the other clans.
チャン家もほかの家のヤツらも
全部まとめて受け入れてやるさ
Just look at you.
なんて顔してんだよ
Don't worry. People from Xing always keep promises, right?
心配すんな　シンの者は
盟約を必ず守るだろ
You'll "accept us all"? That's so greedy, Lin Yao!
全部まとめてなんて
強欲すぎよ　リン·ヤオ…
Shoot, maybe he rubbed off on me.
あいつのがうつったかもなぁ
Well, then... guess we should start heading back.
さて　帰るかな
Already?
行くのか
Yeah.
I want to give Fu a proper burial.
早くフーを埋葬してやりたいしな
Later.
またな
Yup, later.
So many things happened...
いろんなことがあったね
Yeah.
By the way, Alphonse.
時にアルフォンス君
Seems like the princess of Xing,
May Chan, really took a liking to you.
シンの皇女様　メイ·チャン様に
随分と気に入られていたようですが
ほんと　いい子だよね
Yeah, she's such a nice girl.
Moving right along, what about things between you and Winry?
それより兄さん
ウィンリィのこと　いいの
Den! It's me!
デン　僕だよ
Customers...?
お客さんかな
デン　くすぐったいよ
Den, that tickles!
Welcome home, idiots!
バカ　おかえり
Yo!
Good to be home!
ただいま
Oww!!
2 Years Later
痛ててっ
I suck at stuff like this...
苦手なんだよなぁ～
やっぱ　無理か
Nothing, huh...
まあいっか
Ah, well.
兄さん　まだ直らないの
Brother, you still haven't fixed it yet?
オレはあいさつ回りでくたびれてんだ
I'm all worn out from greeting people.
それをウィンリィのヤツ
Winry knows that, but she's treating me like her slave.
こき使いやがって
よっと
だいたいだな…
On top of that-
アップルパイ焼けたから
She wants you to come down for tea
now that her apple pie is out of the oven.
お茶にしようって　ウィンリィが
Okay.
今日は一段と遠くまで見えるね
We have a pretty amazing view today!
Yeah.
広いね
The world is so vast.
Yup.
兄さん
Brother, there's something that's been on my mind for a while.
僕　ずっと考えてたことがある
たぶん　オレも同じこと考えてる
I'm probably thinking of the same thing.
どうですか　お仕事の方は
How is your work?
いやはや　問題が山積みで
There are so many things to worry about; I feel like I suddenly aged twenty years.
一気に老け込みました
とはいえ
But I have Mustang and Armstrong fulfilling their duties in the east and the north, respectively.
東はマスタング君
北はアームストロング君が
しっかりやってくれていますので
この老いぼれもなんとか
Thanks to them, an old geezer like me can somehow manage to perform my duties as the Führer President.
大総統のイスに座っていられます
有り難いことです
I really owe them a lot.
後進に　お譲りにならないの
Are you not going to give away your position?
まだまだ　若い者には譲れません
I can't hand it over to the young ones just yet.
あらまあ
Oh, my.
亡くなった
You sound just like my late husband.
ブラッドレイみたいなことを言うのね
あの人も仕事一辺倒だったのよ
He was always totally committed to work, like you are.
いやいや　私はこのうえなく…
Oh no, I'm the most...
不まじめですよ
...irresponsible person I know.
あら　セリム　どうしたの
Oh my, Selim.
What's the matter?
小鳥さん　ケガしてるの　助けて
This little birdy is hurt.
Could you help him?
あらあら　大変
Oh, no.
じいやに獣医を呼んでもらいなさい
Have the butler call a veterinarian.
治る　小鳥さん　治る
Will... Will he get better?
大丈夫よ　さあ　お行きなさい
Of course he will.
Run along now.
優しい子に育ちましたな
He's grown into such a kind boy.
He has.
あの子を育てると決めたとき
Everyone protested when I decided I'd raise him,
みんなに反対されましたけど
なんの心配もなく　すくすくと
but he's grown so much without giving me reason to worry.
まだ しばらく見守らせてもらいますよ
We're going to be keeping an eye on him for just a little while longer.
あの子に異変が起きたときは…
You're aware what we'll have to do...
分かっておりますな
...if he causes trouble, right?
私が起こさせませんわ
I won't let him.
人造人間と人間
A homunculus and a human.
果たして真に心を通わせることができるのか
Will they really be able to understand each other?
新たな可能性というやつは
New possibilities get you excited no matter how old you are.
いくつになってもワクワクするねぇ
エドワード君
Is Edward not depressed about his left leg?
左足のことで落ち込んでない
Not at all.
大丈夫です
自分を戒めるためにも
He even said, "As punishment, I'd rather keep my leg as an automail."
足は機械鎧のままでいいって
言ってました
そう
I see.
それに　「これがないと
He also said, "Winry'll cry if I don't have this."
ウィンリィが嘆くだろ」って
なぁに　そのノロケ
What in the world?
本当に元に戻ってよかった
I'm so glad you two got your bodies back.
あの人も喜ぶわ
I'm sure Maes will be happy too.
ヒューズさんをはじめ
Starting with Mr. Hughes,
いろんな場所で
So many different people from so many different places helped us be happy.
いろんな人にたくさん…
本当にたくさん  幸せを頂きました
だから　今度は僕らが
And that's why I feel like it's our turn to give back.
お返しする番だと思うんです
錬金術師が言うところの
Is that what you alchemists call "Equivalent Exchange"?
等価交換
いえ　１０もらって
Nope. If we received 10 and gave 10 back,
everything would be the same.
１０返すだけじゃ同じなので
１０もらったら
If we receive 10, we add an extra and give back 11.
自分の１を上乗せして
１１にして返す
小さいけど　僕たちがたどりついた
It's very minor, but it's a new rule my brother and I came up with.
新しい法則です
これから　証明していかなきゃ
But now we're going to have to live up to our word.
いけないんですけど
何かやりたいことがあるのね
There's something you want to do, isn't there?
僕たちが助けられなかった
There's a girl we couldn't save.
女の子がいました
その子をずっと忘れることができません
We still can't forget about her.
いらっしゃいませ
Welcome!
ジェルソさん　ザンパノさん
Mr. Jerso, Mr. Zampano.
Yo.
いっぱいあるぞ　食え
We've got a ton of food. Eat up.
はい
Okay.
すいませ～ん
Excuse me! Can I get a glass of milk and a sandwich?
牛乳とサンドイッチ　追加で
は～い
Coming right up!
そうか　あいさつは済んだのか
I see. So you've already paid your respects.
はい
Yup.
それじゃあ　いよいよ…
Then it's...
だな
...time.
シンに行くよ
I'm going to Xing.
メイのところで
I plan on studying Eastern Alchemy full-scale at May's place.
本格的に錬丹術を学ぶつもりだ
シンだけじゃない
Not just Xing.
東方の国々を回って
I want to go around all the eastern countries to study various things.
さまざまな学問を
身に付けたいと思ってる
いろんなものを見たい
I want to see and learn many things.
いろんなことを知りたい
いろんな人に会いたいんだ
I also want to meet many new people.
っていうか　本当についてくるの
But wait, are you two really coming along?
当たり前よ
Of course!
おめぇについていきゃ
Our wild instincts tell us...
いいことがあるってな
...that coming along with you...
ささやくんだよ
オレたちの 野生の勘がな
...will get us something great!!
アルフォンス
Alphonse.
オレたちは元の体に戻る方法を探す
We're going to look for a way to return to our old bodies.
あきらめるなって言ったのはお前だぞ
You're the one who told us not to give up.
人に任せないで
We have to do things ourselves
instead of having others do the work.
自分で動かないとな
Right!
兄貴はシンに行かねぇのか
Isn't your brother coming to Xing?
Nah.
僕は東回り　兄さんは西回りで
I'm taking the eastern route,
and he's taking the western route.
知識を身に付けてくる
そして二人で東西の知識を持ち寄れば
And once the two of us gather the knowledge we gained from both directions,
ニーナみたいな不幸を
we may be able to avoid the same kind of tragedy that happened to Nina.
繰り返さずに済むかもしれない
でもね…
But, you know...
兄さんも僕も
That's not the only reason why we're traveling.
それだけじゃないんだよ
見てみたいんだ　世界の広さを
We want to see just how vast the world is!
毎日　油をさすこと
You need to oil it every day.
Sure.
ネジの緩みもチェックすること
And check to make sure all the screws are tight.
Sure.
お風呂上がりに水分ふき取ること
Dry it off after coming out of the shower.
Sure...
ちょっと　聞いてるの
Hey, are you even listening?!
Sure...
もう～
Geez...
Well, here it is!
来た来た
ほんと　もう～
With this attitude, you're just going to end up
breaking it and having to come back again soon.
そんなんじゃ　すぐまた壊して
戻ってくるはめになるわよ
へいへい　分かってます
Yeah, yeah, I know.
整備が必要なときは
When you need maintenance,
be sure to call in for an appointment.
ちゃんと予約の電話入れてね
Sure.
予約…
Appointment...
何
What?
ウィンリィ…
Winry...
何よ　はっきり言いなさいよ
What is it? Just speak up if you've got something to say.
等価交換だ
It's equivalent exchange!
オレの人生　半分やるから
I'll give you half of my life, so you give me half of yours!
お前の人生　半分くれ
Oh, geez!
もう　錬金術師って
Why do alchemists have to be like this?
どうしてそうなの「等価交換の法則」とかって
"Equivalent Exchange"? Are you retarded?
バッカじゃないの
なんだと
What did you say?!
ほんっと　バカね
You really are stupid.
半分どころか　全部あげるわよ
Half? I'll give you all of it.
W-Wait, maybe not all of it!
やっぱり　全部はなし
９割…いや　８割かな
90 percent...
Or maybe.. 80 percent?
７じゃないな…じゃあ　８.５
A bit more than 70...
Okay then, 85 percent?
そうよ　そのくらいなら
Sure! I can give you that much!
あげてもいいわよ
何よ
W-What?!
エド
Ed!
My bad, my bad.
悪ぃ　悪ぃ
エド
Ed!!
お前　やっぱ　すげぇわ
You really are amazing.
等価交換の法則なんざ
You're able to overturn the law of equivalent exchange so easily.
簡単にひっくり返しやがる
何よそれ  バカにしてんの
What do you mean by that?
Are you making fun of me?
違ぇよ
I'm not.
元気もらった　ありがとな
That cheered me up. Thanks.
行ってくる
I'll be off now.
いってらっしゃい
Safe trip!
Oh my, even Edward left on a trip?
エドワード君も旅に出ちまったのかい
ちっとは落ち着いたらいいのにねぇ
Why don't they settle down a little?
あいつらはこれでいいんです
For them, this is fine.
じっとしてる男なんて
Men who keep still are no fun.
つまんないもの
痛みを伴わない教訓には意義がない
A lesson without pain is meaningless.
人は何かの犠牲なしには
That's because no one can gain without sacrificing something.
何も得ることはできないのだから
しかしその痛みに耐え　乗り越えたとき
But by enduring that pain and overcoming it...
人は何ものにも負けない
...he shall obtain a powerful, unmatched heart.
強靱な心を手に入れる
そう　鋼のような心
A fullmetal heart.
Drawn by a landscape as white as snow,
Masshiro na keshiki ni ima sasowarete
I'm headed toward an unseen world.
Boku wa yuku yo mada minu sekai e
I've been traveling while lost
Maigo no mama tabi shiteita
Under this gray sky.
Nezumiiro no sora no shita
Every day with new maps, stained with my many dreams.
Higawari no chizu ikutsumo no yume ga nijindeita
I wonder if someday,
Itsuka wa sa
Even with these tiny steps of mine,
Chippoke na boku no kono hohaba demo
I'll be able to travel beyond those clouds.
Ano kumo no mukou made yukeru kana
I put on a bold front.
Tsuyogatte
End up hurting myself.
Kizutsuita
I feel empty inside.
Kokoro sukashita youni
It's started to rain,
Furidashita
And the raindrops
Amatsubu tachi ga
Began to repeat their scattered reflections.
Ranhansha kurikaesu
These straight rays of light
Massugu na hikari ga
Start to cross one another.
Kousa shite
And without telling anyone where they're headed,
Yakusaki mo tsugenumama
Across the endless distances,
Doko made mo
They pass through all matter.
Tsukinukeru
I burn these faint afterimages onto my eyes.
Awai zanzou ryoume ni yakitsukete
Under this sky,
Kono sora no shita
Wherever I am,
Donna toko ni itemo
I should be able to reach
Todoku hazu nanda
The unseen world.
Mada minu sekai e
日本語字幕仕上げ：XIAOBIN
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs